Pedro E. Harunari

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER · STATISTICAL PHYSICS

Department of Physics and Materials Science, University of Luxembourg, Campus Limpertsberg, 162a avenue de la Faïencerie, L-1511 Luxembourg (G. D. Luxembourg)

■ pedro.harunari@uni.lu | Wovember 15th, 1995 | Apedroharunari.github.io/website/

Personal Profile

Currently, I hold a postdoctoral researcher position at the University of Luxembourg, working under the supervision of Prof. Massimiliano Esposito. My Ph.D. in physics was obtained in 2022 from the University of São Paulo, Brazil, where I engaged in extensive research and teaching activities. As an active researcher in statistical physics, my focus is on understanding and taming fluctuations in systems outside thermal equilibrium, alongside their thermodynamic properties. I am particularly interested in extending the description of stochastic thermodynamics in the presence of hidden degrees of freedom by pinpointing the relevant quantities, devising model-free estimators, and bridging theoretical results to realistic applications, particularly in biophysics, chemical reaction networks, complex systems, and electronics.

Education

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Postdoctoral researcher

Dec 2022 - Current

- Member of the group Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics
- · Supervised by Prof. Massimiliano Esposito

University of São Paulo

São Paulo, Brazil

Doctorate in Physics Mar 2018 - Nov 2022

- Thesis: "The role of time in nonequilibrium: transition-based coarse-graining, phase transitions and heat engines" DOI:10.11606/T.43.2022.tde-14122022-084103
- · Advisor: Prof. Dr. Carlos E. Fiore
- Allowed to join the program without a Master's degree
- · Approved with the highest grades in every course

University of São Paulo

São Paulo, Brazil

Bachelor in Physics

Feb 2014 - Nov 2017

- 1.5 years of research training activities
- Complementary courses at: IMPA, CBPF and ICTP-SAIFR

List of Publications _

13 articles published in internationally renowned journals and 4 preprints.

From Google Scholar: 248 citations, h-index 9.

• PE Harunari, A Garilli, and M Polettini, "The beat of a current"

• M Polettini, PE Harunari , S Dal Cengio, V Lecomte, "Coplanarity of rooted spanning-tree vectors"	
arXiv:2407.16093 (preprint)	2024
• Q Yu, PE Harunari , "Dissipation at limited resolutions: Power law and detection of hidden dissipative scales"	
arXiv:2407.13707 (accepted in Journal of Statistical Mechanics)	2024
• PE Harunari , CE Fiore, AC Barato, "Inference of entropy production for periodically driven systems"	
arXiv:2406.12792 (preprint)	2024
• PE Harunari, S Dal Cengio, V Lecomte, M Polettini, "Mutual linearity of nonequilibrium network currents"	
Physical Review Letters 133, 047401 (Editors' suggestion)	2024
• PE Harunari, "Uncovering Nonequilibrium from Unresolved Events"	
Physical Review E 110 , 024122	2024
• A Garilli, PE Harunari , M Polettini, "Fluctuation relations for a few observable currents at their own beat"	
Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 57 , 455003	2023
• F Avanzini, M Bilancioni, V Cavina, S Dal Cengio, M Esposito, G Falasco, D Forastiere, N Freitas, A Garilli, PE	
Harunari, V Lecomte, A Lazarescu, SGM Srinivas, C Moslonka, I Neri, E Penocchio, WD Piñeros, M Polettini, A	
Raghu, P Raux, K Sekimoto, A Soret, "Methods and Conversations in (Post) Modern Thermodynamics"	
SciPost Phys. Lect. Notes 80	2024
• F Hawthorne, PE Harunari , MJ de Oliveira, CE Fiore, "Nonequilibrium thermodynamics of the majority vote	
model"	
Entropy 25, 1230 (Feature Paper)	2023

Physical Review E 107 , L042105	2022
• PE Harunari, A Dutta, M Polettini, and É Roldán, "What to learn from a few visible transitions' statistics?"	
Physical Review X 12, 041026	2022
• IN Mamede, PE Harunari , BAN Akasaki, K Proesmans, and CE Fiore, "Obtaining efficient thermal engines from	
interacting Brownian particles under time-periodic drivings"	
Physical Review E 105 , 024106	2022
• CE Fiore, PE Harunari , CEF Noa, and GT Landi, "Current fluctuations in nonequilibrium discontinuous phase transitions"	
Physical Review E 104 , 064123	2021
• PE Harunari , S Fernando Filho, CE Fiore, and A Rosas, " <i>Maximal power for heat engines: Role of asymmetric interaction times</i> "	
Physical Review Research 3, 023194	2021
• PE Harunari , CE Fiore, and K Proesmans, " <i>Exact statistics and thermodynamic uncertainty relations for a periodically driven electron pump</i> "	
Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 53 (37), 374001	2020
 CEF Noa, PE Harunari, MJ de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Entropy production as a tool for characterizing nonequilibrium phase transitions" 	
Physical Review E 100 , 012104	2019
• JM Encinas, PE Harunari , MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Fundamental ingredients for discontinuous phase transitions in the inertial majority vote model"	
Scientific reports 8 (1), 1-9	2018
• PE Harunari , MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Partial inertia induces additional phase transition in the majority vote model"	
Physical Review E 96 , 042305	2017

Work Experience

(Post) Modern Thermodynamics - School and workshop

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Organizer • Approximately, 100 participants from abroad and 30 from Luxembourg

- Conference consisting of 10 school lectures, 8 workshop sessions, and one poster session.
- Shared teaching duties of the lecture "Continuous-time Markov chain: basics, first-passages and thermodynamics" with Ken Sekimoto.
- Editorial duties on the preparation of lecture notes "Methods and Conversations in (Post) Modern Thermodynamics".
- Co-organizers: Matteo Polettini, Vasco Cavina, William Piñeros.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Dec 2022

Visiting researcher

May 2022 – Jun 2022

· Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Visiting researcher

Apr 2021 - Feb 2022

- Visitor at Massimiliano Esposito's Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics group.
- Supervised by Matteo Polettini.

University of Aalto Helsinki, Finland Visiting researcher Dec 2021 - Jan 2022

· Visitor at Jukka Pekola's PICO group.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Visiting researcher

Jul 2021 - Sep 2021

Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

Statistical Physics seminar series

online

Organizer

· 21 seminars virtually presented during the COVID lockdown, mostly by professors, for a broad audience of students and researchers across Brazil and other countries. Co-organizer: Carlos E. Fiore.

Undergraduate researcher 2015 - 2017

- · Research training program.
- Supervisors: Mário J. de Oliveira (2015-2016), and Carlos E. Fiore (2016-2017).

Teaching Experience

2024	Classical and Q	Quantum Information [•]	Theory (ខ្	graduate level)	, teacher, University	y of Luxembourg
------	-----------------	----------------------------------	------------	-----------------	-----------------------	-----------------

- Thermodynamics, teaching assistant, University of São Paulo 2020
- 2019 Statistical Mechanics, teaching assistant, University of São Paulo
- 2018 Statistical Mechanics (graduate level), teaching assistant, University of São Paulo
- Statistical Mechanics, teaching assistant, University of São Paulo 2018

Skills

Programming Python, Mathematica, C.

Miscellaneous Usage of clusters, LTFX, Ubuntu Linux, teaching.

Prizes and Grants

Honorable mention for distinguished Ph.D. thesis in Exact and Earth Sciences, University of São Paulo 2023

- Best Ph.D. thesis in Statistical and Computational Physics (national level), Brazilian Physical Society 2023
- 2022 Best Ph.D. thesis prize, Institute of Physics - University of São Paulo
- Honorable mention for distinguished publication, Institute of Physics University of São Paulo 2022
- Intership grant, grant for 11 months of internship abroad (BEPE FAPESP) 2021
- Ph.D. fellowship, FAPESP 4 years grant for the Doctorate without Masters degree program 2018
- **Undergrad research fellowship.** FAPESP grant for the Undergraduate research program 2017
- 2016 **Undergrad research fellowship**, CNPq grant for the Undergraduate research program

Events attended

Dissipative Processes in Molecular Systems

University of Padova

· Poster: "Inferring dissipation by monitoring reservoirs"

Journées de Physique Statistique, 42nd edition

École Normale Supérieure de Paris

• Talk: "Unveiling nonequilibrium from multifilar events"

XXVII Sitges Conference on Statistical Mechanics

Universitat de Barcelona

NORDITA

• Talk: "Thermodynamics at the beat of transitions"

Workshop on Stochastic Thermodynamics - WOST IV

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

· Talk: "Fluctuation relation at the beat of a current"

Physics of Life: Students and Postdocs Edition

The Center for the Physics of Biological Function, CUNY/Princeton

• Talk: "Thermodynamics through the lens of transitions"

Fluctuations and First Passage Problems

• Talk: "Thermodynamics at the beat of transitions"

Journées de Physique Statistique, 42nd edition

École Normale Supérieure de Paris

• Talk: "Transition-based coarse-graining"

The 47th Conference of the Middle European Cooperation in Statistical Physics

MECO 47

• Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"

Padova, Italy

2024

Paris, France

2024

Sitges, Spain

New York, United States of America

online

2023

Stockholm, Sweden

Paris, France

Erice, Italy

2022

Autumn meeting São Paulo, Brazil Brazilian Physical Society 2022 • Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions" **National Statistical Physics Meeting** online Universidade Federal de São João del-Rei (UFSJ) 2021 • Talk: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions" **Statistical Physics of Complex Systems** Trieste, Italy The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) 2021 • Poster: "Entropy production fluctuation in phase transitions" **Bangalore School on Statistical Physics XII** online International Center for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS) **Autumn meeting** online **Brazilian Physical Society** 2021 • Talk: "Entropy Production fluctuations in nonequilibrium transitions" **Workshop on Stochastic Thermodynamics - WOST II** online Santa Fe Institute **APS March Meeting** online American Physical Society • Talk: "Quantitative compartison of different time-periodic Thermodynamic Uncerainty Relations" **Quantum Thermodynamics of Non-equilibrium systems** online Donostia International Physics Center 2020 **Statistical Physics Seminar Series** online University of São Paulo • Talk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: Schnakenberg, FT and TUR" **Autumn meeting** online **Brazilian Physical Society** 2020 • Talk: "Stochastic pump as a model to study nonequilibrium properties" **Quantum Thermodynamics for Young Scientists** Bad Honnef, Germany Wilhelm and Else Heraeus-Foundation Poster: "Time assymetric reciprocity relations for an arbitrarily long single-particle stochastic pump and its exact solution" "Coloquinho" São Paulo, Brazil series of talks organized by IFT-UNESP, ICTP-SAIFR students 2019 • Invited talk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: basics and some modern aspects" **Physics Giants: Einstein Week** São Paulo, Brazil series of talks organized by USP students 2019 • Invited talk: "Einstein's contributions to Statistical Mechanics" Languages_ **English** Full professional proficiency **Portuguese** Native proficiency **Spanish** Limited working proficiency

Peer-review contributions

PRL, PRX, PRX Quantum, PRE, PRA, JPhysA, JPhyComm